Where did I put it...?
I know it's in here somewhere...
Huh...?
Found it.
Let's go.
Mm-hmm.
Rajdhani!
What is this? Something Indian?
You two are going home, right?
Mm-hmm.
Well, would you let me lend you a hand?
I know I can be of some help to you.
Mm-hmm, we'd love that.
This...
...says that about 2,000 years
has passed, doesn't it?
Yeah, and what happened
to that cool ship you had?
Oh, now... We'll have
plenty of time for that.
I'll tell you all about it on the way.
Okay...
Huh?
Final draft! Project Robinson Ver 3.0
Nagara, did you put all this
together?
This is incredible!
Hmm, if we take this... and do that...
There, it's perfect.
What do you think?
Pretty handy, right?
Mm-hmm, that is awesome.
Awesome! Awesome!
Okay,
we're good here.
Nagara!
Can you take it from here?
Mm-hmm, all right.
Hey, Mizuho.
You're not going to use that over there?
Nah, I can do what
I need from here.
Besides,
as long as I'm doing this,
I want to watch it with my own eyes.
So you really aren't going
to come home with us, then?
Mm-mm. I'm staying here.
Rajdhani, didn't you ever feel homesick?
You were all by yourself
for 2,000 years, weren't you?
Homesick... now there's
a sensation that takes me back.
There was a world that I stopped by before
that painted really close pictures
of scenes from my old home.
They were shockingly accurate and vivid,
but most of all, mysterious.
So much so that they made me feel uneasy.
That was the first time since we went
adrift that I felt any sense of nostalgia.
I decided to call that
This World "Homesick."
By "old home," do you mean
the world we came from?
Yeah, but also, kind of different.
The world was more "our-world-like"
than it was "our world."
The master of that world was almost
pathologically caught up in his memories,
and kept recreating his homeland.
The strange thing was,
no matter how far you went in this world,
there was never another soul
represented anywhere.
Sounds like a lonely place.
But then, when a certain time approached,
the style radically changed.
When I saw those images,
I was taken aback.
They were the likeness
of this one female student.
She was depicted as
a real beauty, you know?
Apparently, this girl
used to be his girlfriend.
This is starting to get interesting.
Isn't it?
I gave in to my curiosity, too.
I took a look at her with my Scoop Scope,
a power holdover that I developed myself.
Yeah, and...?
The actual girl was not
nearly as pretty as her image.
Those love goggles come
with a strong prescription.
However, the girl really did love him.
It got me curious,
so I peered into the other images.
His actual home was a town that I knew,
which wasn't as beautiful or nearly
as attractive as how he had depicted it.
Put simply, he didn't accept reality.
His girlfriend wanted him to live
in the reality in front of his eyes.
But he refused to change.
So eventually, she got fed up with him,
and she left that world.
So then he began painting pictures
of his girlfriend like a man possessed.
That figure of her was
what was in the paintings.
It felt as though I had been
unexpectedly confronted by reality.
I thought, can I say I'm actually
living my own life in reality?
She didn't want to create
beautiful memories with him;
she wanted to create a future
with him that was still unformed.
At some point, he became
a captive to his memories of her,
and that became his entire world.
Did he die?
Hmm, I'm not sure
exactly how to answer that.
Death in This World is
a little bit complicated.
When I think about dying,
it's dark, and scary,
and makes my chest feel tight.
I wonder if that's how
it was for Nozomi, too.
Did she feel afraid?
Nagara,
have you been to see
the world where Nozomi died?
Mm-mm.
Then how were you able
to make certain that she died?
I see. Mizuho's cat, huh?
She is able to tell...
...the status of all things.
There was an inventor in one world.
The students who were in that world
believed themselves to
be the children of God,
and were convinced that they had
to keep their minds and bodies spotless.
They made up their minds
to live without killing,
without eating meat,
and to not even kill any plants.
That was a world of fasting.
Sounds like an awfully difficult world.
No, actually, they seemed
surprisingly happy.
That world flourished with a beautiful,
advanced civilization,
and had a lot of
holdovers remaining in it.
Wow, you don't say.
For one thing,
hunger isn't that big a deal to us.
On the fringe of that world,
there was a student who
was obsessed with dying.
He was trying to produce
death here in this static world—
an inventor of "death."
Invent "death"?
Yeah.
He was trying to upset the stasis
of this world through people's deaths.
To tell you the truth,
I kind of admired him a little.
His sense of morals aside, this was
a challenge directed at This World.
But then...
...the actual guy was the devil himself.
He reviled God, burned down the forests,
wolfed down meat, and held
those who fasted in contempt.
What's more, he took
advantage of the stasis here
to conduct experiments in suicide
and murder over and over.
This guy sounds like
nothing more than a serial killer.
Yeah.
He was so utterly atrocious,
I honestly felt like killing him myself.
So then, finally, he invented "death."
He... apparently wanted to die so badly,
he couldn't help himself.
So he was the very first person
he used his invention on.
And he died with flying colors.
Uh...
Mm-hmm.
I actually found his invention.
It was like...
...he was telling me to have a seat, too.
Huh? Did you sit down?
He didn't look at all different
from who he was before he died.
But with each passing day,
the changes began appearing.
The inventor no longer had any desires.
He accepted what he saw in
front of him, was content with it,
and no longer offered any
criticism or hatred of anyone.
He became a well-adjusted person,
not unlike a Buddha.
The inventor had left This World.
He knew that when
his drive came to an end,
it marked the end of his life as he was.
This is one form of "death" in This World.
I ended up not sitting down.
Do you suppose he hated himself?
Who knows?
After all this time,
I don't know why he was
so obsessed with dying.
But after living for so long,
I understand something—
as you keep building up all sorts of
experiences and what have you,
there's something about you
that grows more and more irregular.
The larger it gets, the more
individual meanings become diluted,
and the more homogenized
things become, I'd say.
I can tell that I'm steadily growing more
apathetic the more unbalanced I get.
Ultimately, I'll end up as
a gaping, lopsided hole.
I'm being drained away by time,
until someday, I'll become
a mere shape, much like Nozomi has.
But it's nothing more than another
state incorporated into this stasis.
If that can be called "death," then...
...it's no different than
the "death" in our own world.
Yeah. There's no such thing as a soul,
and our consciousness is born
for no reason, then it just fades away.
Life is an endless
exercise in vain effort.
But it's precisely
because it's meaningless
that I think the brilliance of
this moment in life is so precious.
Because that one moment
belongs to that person alone.
Nozomi isn't ever coming back.
But even so...
...her will still lives on.
How much of it is finished?
The cats are doing their best,
but I'd have to say about 20%.
I did try reaching out to the others...
...but they all said
they weren't going back.
It ended up being just
Mizuho and me... and...
...Nozomi who were going.
Doing it like this means that
in going back to our own world,
we might end up not
being who we are anymore,
is that right?
Mm-hmm.
Plus the time it will take.
Even if we do make it back, two years
will have passed since we went adrift.
And there's a chance
that I'll be dead there.
That's true.
Well, there's no use in thinking
about what might happen.
I could just as well be alive, too.
Everything that took place here
could end up as though it never happened.
And if it does...
Hmm?
Never mind.
Tell me, if we do get back...
...what's the first thing you want to do?
I haven't given that any thought.
Why not? It's fun.
Well, I mean, we might not
even remember any of this.
And there's no use in thinking
about what might happen, right?
Huh? Then, are you calling me
a fool for thinking so much about it?
I'm just saying, it's not a big deal.
Hm-hmm, you know what?
I'm going to have a Soleil omu-rice,
something with a ton
of grace strawberries on it,
then eat my fill of
Chinese noodles from Hatsune...
There, you see? I knew it.
What a bunch of nonsense.
After that,
I'm going to find the
curmudgeonly-looking boy
from the corner of the staff room,
grab him by the scruff of the neck,
and ask him a question.
What's that?
"Will you be my friend once again?"
Once I do, what do you
suppose he will answer?
We're already high-schoolers.
Huh?
I just don't know.
Why not?
Well...
...you and me being friends
will have never happened.
You'll have torn up your textbook again,
and I'll have abandoned that bird.
That's not true.
We've made
a lot of progress since then.
There's no telling
if what happened here...
...will still have
happened over there, too.
Still,
they did for sure happen here.
Okay, how about this?
Whichever one of us
remembers has to do as I say.
We have to become friends again.
Okay? Promise me.
Promise me you won't refuse.
Mm-hmm.
No matter how well I've come to understand
the psychology of this universe, I...
...can't do anything more for a friend
who's crying but sit next to him.
Hey, you...!
Rajdhani...
I need to ask you about something.
What is it?
There's one item I want
to add to Project Robinson.
Ah, now we're talking.
I know we can't change the world.
In which case...
Wow, analog-style.
Heh-heh, that's right.
This is the very same rocket that
first took mankind to the moon.
That's good luck, right?
The cat's copies are
accurately reproduced.
And what's up top is even more primitive.
Mizuho,
why did you want to go home?
Because I... have things I want to do.
The cats can't live over there anymore.
Mm-hmm. I know.
Actually, it's pretty easy to
get back to our own world.
But to do so requires
resolve and sacrifice.
We can't get back
the time that has passed.
But you two can still make it.
Still, we're not simply
going back, are we?
Right. Nagara is...
Sorry I'm late.
Now everything is ready.
Tomorrow is the big day.
I've had enough already.
I'm staying here with the others.
If you ever happen to run into me,
it would be my pleasure.
Mm-hmm, got it.
Here.
Yeah, I'll take care of them.
Thanks for everything you've done.
Yamabiko, you take care.
Sakura! See you!
I have to go now!
I...
...left my cats behind.
I'm sure the cats feel the same as we do.
I wonder if Sakura will
watch over them, too.
Mm-hmm.
Fifteen seconds to launch.
Switching to internal power.
Twelve...
...eleven...
ten...
...nine...
Ignition start.
Launch pad safely cleared
and you are on course.
That's all the support I can give you.
Good luck to you.
Copy.
Farewell, Rajdhani.
Hmm, now then...
This...
...must be from Mizuho.
Then, this...
Nothing matters in This World...
...but once in a while,
cool things do happen.
That is why I can get by.